# Weiwei Zhan, Ph.D.

Assistant Professor, University of Central Florida Tel: 407-823-3073

Department of Civil, Environmental and Construction Engineering Email: weiwei.zhan@ucf.edu

12760 Pegasus Dr, Orlando, FL 32816 Website: https://weiwei-zhan.github.io

### RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research interests lie primarily in understanding the complex hazard-infrastructure-human interactions and advancing urban intelligence and resilience. I study multiple geological hazards, such as earthquakes, landslides, and liquefaction, and their effects on infrastructure systems. I use a wide range of approaches, including remote sensing, signal processing, geomaterial testing, computational simulation, statistical learning, machine learning, and deep learning. Main research thrusts include site-specific and regional assessment of earthquake site responses, ground-motion modeling, near-real-time liquefaction hazard assessment, landslide mechanism and mitigation, geospatial surrogate modeling, and uncertainty quantification.

# **ACADEMIC POSITIONS**

Jul. 2023 – now	Assistant Professor	University of Central Florida, USA
Jan. 2023 – Jul. 2023	Postdoctoral Fellow	University of Texas at Austin, USA
	Topic: HPC applications in natura	al hazard engineering
	Advisor: Prof. Ellen Rathje	
Mar. 2021– Dec. 2022	Postdoctoral Scholar	Tufts University, USA
	Topic: Geospatial natural hazard n	nodeling and uncertainty quantification
	Advisor: Prof. Laurie Baise	
Jan. 2017 – Dec 2020	<b>Graduate Research Assistant</b>	Clemson University, USA
	Topic: Probabilistic liquefaction ri	isk assessment
	Advisor: Assoc. Prof. Qiushi Chen	ı
Sep. 2014 – Dec 2016	<b>Graduate Research Assistant</b>	Chengdu University of Technology, China
	Topic: Landslide mechanism and r	risk mitigation design
	Advisors: Prof. Xuanmei Fan, Prof.	f. Runqiu Huang

### **EDUCATION**

2020	Ph.D. in Civil Engineering	Clemson University, USA
	Thesis: Data-driven assessment of site respo	nses at liquefiable sites
	Advisor: Assoc. Prof. Qiushi Chen	
2019	M.Sc. in Civil Engineering (non-thesis)	Clemson University, USA
	Advisor: Assoc. Prof. Qiushi Chen	
2014	B.S. in Geological Engineering	Chengdu University of Technology, China
	Thesis: Statistical modeling of coseismic lan	dslide mobility
	Advisors: Prof. Xiangjun Pei, Prof. Weile Li	

#### **AWARDS & HONORS**

2022	Travel Grant for 2022 SimCenter Symposium, NHERI SimCenter (UC Berkeley)
2022	Travel Grant for 12NCEE, Earthquake Engineering Research Institute (EERI)
2016	National Scholarship, Ministry of Education of China
2016	Travel Grant for International Rockslides School, Chengdu University of Technology
2014	Top 10 Bachelor's Thesis (10/8000), Chengdu University of Technology

2014	Meritorious Mention in National Mathematical Modeling Contest, Madio.net
2013	Honorable Mention in the International Mathematics Modeling Competition (MCM/ICM)
	Consortium for Mathematics and Its Application (COMAP)
2012	Excellent Volunteer, Environmental Protection Agency of Sichuan Province

# **TEACHING & MENTORING**

Teaching	
2018 - 2020	Instructor, Soil Mechanics Lab
2020	Teaching Assistant, Geotechnical Engineering
2018 - 2019	Teaching Assistant, Earth Slopes and Retaining Structures
2019	Teaching Assistant, Geotechnical Design
2018	Teaching Assistant, Data Mining for System Analytics
2018	Teaching Assistant, Uncertainty Modeling in Risk Engineering
2017	Teaching Assistant, Fundamentals of Risk Engineering
Mentoring	
2021 - 2022	Mentor for two Ph.D. students at Tufts Univ. (Marshall Pontrelli & Christina Sanon),
	"Geospatial Database and Modeling"
2020	Mentor for two undergraduate student interns at Clemson Univ. (William Luce &
	Christopher Michael Overton), "Mechanical Properties of Lunar Regolith Simulants"
2019	Mentor for three undergraduate student interns at Clemson Univ. (Andrew Bradley, Jason
	Timberlake, & William Luce), "CT morphology for Martian Regolith Simulants"
2018	Mentor for three high school student interns at South Carolina Governor's School for
	Science and Mathematics (Frankie Hawkesworth, Olivia Hilferty, & Jason Gleaton),
	"Strength Tests of Bio-Cemented Martian Regolith Simulants"

# SUCCESSFUL PROPOSALS & GRANTS

2022	U.S. Geological Survey Earthquake Hazards Program External Grant, G23AP00093
	HVSR Site Terms for Nonergodic Ground Motion Models, \$96,583
	(PI: Laurie Baise & James Kaklamanos)
2022	U.S. Geological Survey Earthquake Hazards Program External Grant, G23AP00094
	Basin Effects Model Using Multi-Scale Geospatial Data, \$95,123
	(PI: Laurie Baise & James Kaklamanos)
2021	U.S. Geological Survey Earthquake Hazards Program External Grant, G22AP00048
	Innovative Data-Driven Frameworks for Geospatial Ground Failure Models, \$97,123
	(PI: Laurie Baise & Babak Moaveni)
2021	U.S. Geological Survey Earthquake Hazards Program External Grant
	Machine Learning Framework for Site Amplification Modeling (Recommended but not
	funded due to insufficient funds), PI: Laurie Baise & James Kaklamanos

# **SUBMITTED PAPERS**

- 3. **Zhan W**, Baise LG, Kaklamanos J. A geospatial model for site response complexity. *Bulletin of the Seismological Society of America*. (under revision)
- 2. **Zhan W**, Cochran E. Reducing aleatory uncertainty of ground-motion modeling using gradient boosting model and feature selection techniques. *Bulletin of the Seismological Society of America*. (under revision)

1. **Zhan W**, Baise LG, Moaveni B. A Quantifying Uncertainty Framework for Geospatial Natural Hazard Modeling. *Engineering Geology*. (under revision)

#### PAPERS IN PREPARATION

- 2. **Zhan W**, Baise LG, Moaveni B, Chansky A, et al. Updating Global Geospatial Liquefaction Models with a Focus on Feature Engineering. Targeting *Engineering Geology*.
- 1. **Zhan W**, Baise LG, Moaveni B, Chansky A, et al. OpenLIQ: An Open-Source Geospatial Dataset for Global Liquefaction Hazard Assessment. Targeting *Earthquake Spectra*.

# PEER-REVIEWED JOURNAL PAPERS

(\*corresponding author)

- 14. Zhang L, **Zhan W**, Wang L\* (2023). Probabilistic Seismic Analyses of Earthen Levees with Finite Element Modeling. *Marine Georesources & Geotechnology*, 1-8.
- 13. Wu R, Guo C\*, Ni J, Song D, **Zhan W**, Zhong N, Yang Z, Li X, Yan Y (2023). Ancient landslide river damming event in the Batang fault zone, Tibetan Plateau. *Bulletin of Engineering Geology and the Environment*, 82(1): 25.
- 12. Li W, **Zhan W\***, Lu H, Xu Q, Pei X, Wang D, Huang R, Ge D (2022). Precursors to large rockslides visible on optical remote-sensing images and their implications for landslide early detection. *Landslides*, DOI 10.1007/s10346-022-01960-1.
- 11. Lu J, Li W\*, **Zhan W**, Tie Y (2022). Distribution and mobility of co-seismic landslides triggered by the 2018 Hokkaido earthquake in Japan. *Remote Sensing*, 14, 3957.
- 10. **Zhan W**, Chen Q\* (2022). Nonlinear site response on liquefiable sites: insights from downhole seismic observations. *Engineering Geology*, Article 106610.
- 9. Luo Y, Xu Q, **Zhan W**, Grelle G (2022). Seismic hazard prediction using multispectral amplification maps in a complex topographic area: A case study of Qiaozhuang town, Sichuan Province, Southwest China. *Journal of Mountain Science*, 19: 726–739.
- 8. Shan S, Pei X, **Zhan W\*** (2021). Estimating deformation modulus and bearing capacity of deep soils from dynamic penetration test. *Advances in Civil Engineering*, Article 1082050.
- 7. **Zhan W**, Chen Q\* (2021). Accelerogram-based method for quick assessment of liquefaction occurrence. *Journal of Geotechnical and Geoenvironmental Engineering*, 147 (8): 04021060.
- 6. Gao G, Meguid MA, Chouinard LE, **Zhan W** (2021). Dynamic disintegration processes accompanying transport of an earthquake-induced landslide. *Landslides*, 18 (3): 909-933.
- 5. Fan X, **Zhan W\***, Dong X, van Westen C, Xu Q, Dai L, Yang Q, Huang R, Havenith HB (2018). Analyzing successive landslide dam formation by different triggering mechanisms: The case of the Tangjiawan landslide, Sichuan, China. *Engineering Geology*, 243: 128-144.
- 4. Fan X\*, Scaringi G, Xu Q, **Zhan W**, Dai L, Li Y, Pei X, Yang Q, Huang R (2018). Coseismic landslides triggered by the 8th August 2017 M s 7.0 Jiuzhaigou earthquake (Sichuan, China): factors controlling their spatial distribution and implications for the seismogenic blind fault identification. *Landslides*, 15(5): 967-983.
- 3. Meng X, Pei X\*, Huang R, Cui S, Zhu L, **Zhan W** (2018). Shear behaviors of rock mass in the interlayer fault zone of Daguangbao landslide. *Journal of Engineering Geology*, 26 (2): 309-318. (in Chinese)
- 2. **Zhan W**, Fan X\*, Huang R, Pei X, Xu Q, Li W (2017). Empirical prediction for travel distance of channelized rock avalanches in the Wenchuan earthquake area. *Natural Hazards & Earth System Sciences*, 17(6): 833-844.
- 1. **Zhan W**, Huang R, Pei X, Li W (2017). Empirical prediction model for movement distance of gully-type rock avalanches. *Journal of Engineering Geology*, 25 (1): 154-163. (*in Chinese*)

#### PEER-REVIEWED CONFERENCE PAPERS

- 5. **Zhan W**, Baise LG, Kaklamanos J (2023). Predicting Within-Site Variability of Seismic Site Response Using a Geospatial Modeling Approach, *Geo-Risk 2023*, Arlington, Virginia, July 23-26, 2023. (*feature paper & plenary presentation*, 9 of 163 papers)
- 4. **Zhan W**, Zhang L, Wang L (2023). Probabilistic Assessment of Earthen Levees Considering Soil Spatial Variability, *Geo-Risk 2023*, Arlington, Virginia, July 23-26, 2023. (*accepted*)
- 3. **Zhan W**, Chen Q (2022). Evaluation of an accelerogram-based liquefaction detection method using continuous earthquake recordings. *GeoCalgary 2022*, Calgary, Canada, October 2-5, 2022.
- 2. **Zhan W**, Chen Q (2021). Assessment of liquefaction effects on ground motion frequency parameters for accelerogram-based liquefaction detection, *American Society of Civil Engineers (ASCE) Geotechnical Engineering for Extreme Events (GeoExtreme)* 2021, Savannah, GA, USA, November 7-10, 2021.
- 1. **Zhan W**, Baise LG, Chen Q, Juang CH, Miao F (2021). Effects of liquefaction-affected ground motions on building fragility curves, *17th World Conference on Earthquake Engineering*, Sendai, Japan, September 27-October 2, 2021.

#### **PRESENTATIONS**

(\*presenter)

- 16. Rathje E\*, **Zhan W**, Durante MG (2023). Regional Risk Assessment: Liquefaction, 2023 GEM Conference, Bergamo, Italy, June 13, 2023 (Virtual talk).
- 15. **Zhan W\***, Baise LG, Moaveni B (2023). Updating Global Geospatial Liquefaction Models: with Focus on Uncertainty Quantification and Feature Engineering, *USGS Geologic Hazards Science Center Research Seminar*, Golden, Colorado, USA, January 31, 2023 (*Invited seminar talk*).
- 14. **Zhan W\***, Baise LG, Moaveni B, Chansky A, et al (2023). Updating Global Geospatial Liquefaction Models with a Focus on Feature Engineering. *Seismological Society of America (SSA) 2023 Annual Meeting*, San Juan, Puerto Rico, April 17-20, 2023. (*Oral presentation*)
- 13. **Zhan W\***, Baise LG, Moaveni B (2023). How to Quantify Uncertainties for Logistic-Regression-Based Geospatial Natural Hazard Models? *Seismological Society of America (SSA) 2023 Annual Meeting*, San Juan, Puerto Rico, April 17-20, 2023. (*Poster presentation*)
- 12. Asadi A\*, Baise LG, Chatterjee S, **Zhan W**, Chansky A, Moaveni B (2023). Global Geospatial Modeling of Earthquake-Induced Soil Liquefaction Using a System of Voting Machine Learning Classifiers. *Seismological Society of America (SSA) 2023 Annual Meeting*, San Juan, Puerto Rico, April 17-20, 2023. (*Oral presentation*)
- 11. **Zhan W\***, Baise LG, Moaveni B (2022). Quantifying epistemic uncertainty for global geospatial liquefaction models, *2022 SimCenter Symposium*, Austin, Texas, USA, November 3-4, 2022. (*Oral presentation*)
- 10. **Zhan W\***, Baise LG, Moaveni B (2022). Uncertainty quantification for global geospatial liquefaction models, *Natural Hazards Research Summit 2022*, Washington, DC, USA, October 6-7, 2022. (*Poster presentation*)
- 9. **Zhan W\***, Baise LG, Kaklamanos J (2022). A geospatial model for predicting site response complexity. *Seismological Society of America (SSA) 2022 Annual Meeting*, Bellevue, Washington, USA, April 19-23, 2022. (*Oral presentation*)
- 8. **Zhan W\***, Baise LG, Kaklamanos J (2022). Ground-motion modeling using machine learning techniques and geospatial proxies. *Seismological Society of America (SSA) 2022 Annual Meeting*, Bellevue, Washington, USA, April 19-23, 2022. (*Poster presentation*)
- 7. Pontrelli MA\*, Baise LG, Ebel JE, Mabee SB, Zhan W (2022). Geology and Geomorphology Based f0

- Model of New England. Seismological Society of America (SSA) 2022 Annual Meeting, Bellevue, Washington, USA, April 19-23, 2022. (Poster presentation)
- 6. **Zhan W\***, Chen Q (2021). Assessment of liquefaction effects on ground motion frequency parameters for accelerogram-based liquefaction detection, *American Society of Civil Engineers (ASCE) Geotechnical Engineering for Extreme Events (GeoExtreme) 2021*, Savannah, GA, USA, November 7-10, 2021. (*Oral presentation*)
- 5. **Zhan W\***, Baise LG, Chen Q, Juang CH, Miao F (2021). Effects of liquefaction-affected ground motions on building fragility curves, *17th World Conference on Earthquake Engineering*, Sendai, Japan, September 27-October 2, 2021. (*Virtual poster presentation*)
- 4. Gong, W, **Zhan W\***, Wang L, Juang CH (2021). Design of Stabilizing Piles in Earth Slopes Considering Design Robustness, *Engineering Mechanics Institute Conference/Probabilistic Mechanics and Reliability (EMI/PMC) 2021 Conference*, Columbia University, New York City, USA, May 25-28, 2021. (*Virtual oral presentation*)
- 3. **Zhan W\***, Chen Q (2020). Quick detection of subsoil liquefaction using accelerograms. *2020 AGU Fall Meeting*, San Francisco, CA, USA, December 7-11, 2020. (*Virtual oral presentation*)
- 2. **Zhan W\***, Chen Q (2020). Coseismic and long-term changes of site response on liquefiable sites: a case study of Onahama Port Array in Japan. 2020 Eastern Section of the Seismological Society of America (ES-SSA) Annual Meeting, Atlanta, GA, USA, October 12-16, 2020. (Virtual oral presentation)
- 1. **Zhan W\***, Huang R, Pei X (2015). Study on the Site Effects of Large-scale Landslide movement triggered by Wenchuan Earthquake, *Engineering Geological Disaster Prevention Academic Conference*, Shanghai, China, October 12-14, 2015. (*Oral presentation in Chinese*)

#### **PROFESSIONAL SERVICE**

Convener	2022 SSA Session "Advances in Geospatial Modeling of Seismic Hazards"
Convener	2022 SSA Special Interest Discussion "Modeling of Seismic Site Amplification using AI"
Reviewer	2023 ASCE Geo-Risk, Engineering Geology, Landslides, Lithology, Natural Hazards,
	Frontiers in Earth Science, Bulletin of Engineering Geology and the Environment, Arabian
	Journal of Geosciences, Advances in Civil Engineering, Stochastic Environmental Research
	and Risk Assessment, etc.
Vice President	ASCE Geo-Institute Clemson University Graduate Student Organization
Member	American Society of Civil Engineers Geo-Institute (ASCE G-I)
Member	Earthquake Engineering Research Institute (EERI)
Member	Seismological Society of America
Member	American Geophysical Union